## **NEEL DOSHI**

nddoshi@mit.edu · https://nddoshi.github.io · 516-662-6438

#### **SUMMARY**

Extensive experience with developing algorithms and mechanisms for autonomous robotic manipulation and locomotion. Proven track record of using control, optimization, mechanical design, and machine learning to enhance the capabilities of a wide range of robots, from centimeter-scale legged robots to large industrial robotic arms. Strong ability to collaborate and work in a team environment on multi-disciplinary projects as well as to conceptualize and execute in-depth independent research. U.S. citizen.

## **EDUCATION**

Harvard University

Doctor of Philoshophy, Engineering Sciences

Thesis: Model-based design, control, and planning for legged microrobots

Advisors: Professors Robert J. Wood and Scott Kuindersma

Harvard University

Master of Science, Engineering Sciences (GPA: 4.0/4.0)

Cambridge, MA

Nov 2015

University of Pennsylvania Philadelphia, PA
Master of Science, Robotics (GPA: 3.9/4.0)

May 2013

University of Pennsylvania Philadelphia, PA
Bachelor of Science, summa cum laude, Mechanical Engineering (GPA: 3.83/4.0)

May 2012

Minors: Electrical Engineering, Mathematics

#### SKILLS

- Analytical: Nonlinear and quadratic programming; trajectory optimization; mechanics and dynamics; optimal control; machine learning.
- Software: MATLAB and Simulink; Python; C++; Robot Operating System (ROS).
- Fabrication: SolidWorks; OnShape; DraftSight; 3D printing; laser cutting; laminate manufacturing.
- Languages: English (native); Gujrati (fluent); Hindi (basic).

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA Apr 2019-Present

Postdoctoral Researcher, The MCube Lab

- Developing a framework that combines mechanics, trajectory optimization, and machine learning to enable contact-rich robotic manipulation of unknown or partially known real-world objects.
- Formulated an approach to manipulation of unknown polygonal objects through regulation of their *contact-configuration*: the location, geometry, and mode of all contacts between the object, robot, and environment.
- Collaborated with a team to design and fabricate robotic fingers that simplify dexterous manipulation.

# Harvard University Cambridge, MA

Doctoral Student, Harvard Microrobotics Laboratory

Sep 2013-Mar 2019

- Developed a trajectory optimization based framework to automate the generation of closed-loop locomotion trajectories for computationally limited centimeter-scale legged robots.
- Applied this framework to control the Harvard Ambulatory MicroRobot (HAMR), improving its locomotion speed, stability and efficiency, as well as enabling dynamic behaviors, such as jumping.
- Designed compliant centimeter-scale structures, including robot-feet that allowed HAMR to climb vertical and inverted surfaces as well as transition between terrestrial and aquatic locomotion.

#### University of Pennsylvania

Philadelphia, PA

Research Assistant, ModLab

Mar 2012-July 2013

• Collaborated with a doctoral student to devise an analytic simulator that resolved the hydrodynamics of large elastically linked modular sea-bases for Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) research.

## NASA Goddard Space Flight Center

Greenbelt, MD Summer 2011

Robotics Intern, NASA-GSFC

• Member of a team of five engineers who designed and fabricated a weatherproof thermal enclosure for the electronics of Grover 2 an autonomous rover deployed to explore Greenland's ice sheets.

## **NEEL DOSHI**

## LEADERSHIP AND MANAGEMENT EXPERIENCE

## Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA
Apr 2019-Present

Postdoctoral Researcher, The MCube Lab

- Mentored two doctoral students, one master's student, one research assistant, and one high-school student in the conceptualization and execution of their research. Co-authored publications with all five researchers.
- Established and maintained several cross-disciplinary collaborations that resulted in two publications.

#### Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Doctoral Student, Harvard Microrobotics Laboratory

Sep 2013-Mar 2019

- Co-led a team of five to seven researchers working on HAMR from 2017-2019. Identified research directions.
- Advised or co-advised five masters' students, one research assistant, and four undergraduate students. Co-authored seven publications, including a best paper nominee and two manuscripts in *Science Robotics*.
- Oversaw two undergraduate capstone projects, one of which was awarded the Dean's Design Award.

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

## Planning and control through contact

- 10. N. Doshi\*, O.T. Taylor\* et al., Manipulation of unknown objects via contact configuration regulation. Submitted to the International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2022.
- 9. N. Doshi, et al, Hybrid differential dynamic programming for planar manipulation primitives. ICRA 2020.
- 8. N. Doshi \*, K. Jayaram\*, et al., Effective locomotion atmultiple stride frequencies using proprioceptive feedback on a legged microrobot. Bioinspiration & Biomimetics, 2019.
- 7. Z. Manchester, N. Doshi, R. J. Wood, and S. Kuindersma, Contact-Implicit trajectory optimization using variational integrators. The International Journal of Robotics Research (IJRR) 2019.
- 6. N. Doshi, et al., Contact-implicit optimization of locomotion trajectories for a quadrupedal microrobot. Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS) 2018.

## Design for manipulation and locomotion

- 5. R. Jiang, N. Doshi et. al, Shape and Motion Optimization of Rigid Planar Manipulators for Contact Trajectory Satisfaction. Submitted to ICRA 2022.
- 4. I. H. Taylor et al. including **N. Doshi**, *PnuGrip: An active two-phase gripper for dexterous manipulation*. International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) 2020.
- 3. S. D. Rivaz et al. including **N. Doshi**, Inverted and vertical climbing of a quadrupedal microrobot using electroadhesion. Science Robotics 2018.
- 2. Y. Chen, N. Doshi, et al. Controllable water surface to underwater transition through electrowetting in a hybrid terrestrial-aquatic microrobot. Nature Communications 2018.
- 1. N. Doshi et al., Model driven design for flexure-based microrobots. IROS 2015.

## AWARDS AND RECOGNITION

**Fellowships:** Intelligence Community Postdoctoral Research Fellowship from  $2019-2021^{\dagger}$ ; National Defense Science and Engineering Graduate (NDSEG) Fellowship from  $2014-2017^{\dagger}$ ; Honorable Mention, National Science Foundation (NSF) Graduate Fellowship (2014).

Best Paper/Project Awards: RA-L Best Paper Award for 2020; Finalist, Best Conference Paper Award at ICRA 2018; Finalist, Best Conference Paper Award at IROS 2017; Winner, Best Automation Paper at ICRA 2014; William K. Gemmill Memorial Award for Senior Design Project (2012).

**Popular Press:** Publication #3 covered in Wired, TechTimes, Tech Xplore, +15 more (2018); Publication #2 covered in Popular Mechanics, Science Daily, My Science +75 more (2018).

## INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY

N.C. Dafle, A. Rodriguez, **N. Doshi**, and I. Taylor, *PnuGrip: an active two-phase gripper for dexterous manipulations.* Provisional Application, 2020.

For a full academic CV, see https://nddoshi.github.io/assets/pdfs/FullCV.pdf.

<sup>\*</sup>contributed equally

<sup>†</sup>full funding